Finding Aid for the Kurt Louis Flatau papers, ca. 1940-1950 LSC.1564
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kurt Louis Flatau papers
ca. 1940-1950
UCLA Library Special Collections
Flatau, Kurt Louis
LSC.1564
2.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Kurt Louis Flatau (1895-1950) wrote for various newspapers, lectured on world affairs, gave news commentaries on radio stations KMPC and KMTR (now KLAC), and was the political editor for Fortnight magazine. The collection consists of Flatau's radio broadcast scripts with related news clippings, and clippings of his regular columns for the Los Angeles Daily News and the Los Angeles Times.
Restrictions on Access
Stored off-site. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Brigitte Yallen, 1988.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9912181033606533
Biography
Flatau was born in 1895 in Berlin, Germany; Ph.D, University of Gottingen, 1920; wrote for various newspapers and was the manager of Mamorhaus Theater, Berlin; left Germany for Spain, 1933; headed Iberica Films in Barcelona (1933-36); left for France, 1936; founded Trianon Films in Paris; produced Boulot Aviateur and L'Affaire Lafarge; joined French Army at the beginning of World War II; came to Los Angeles, 1941; lectured on world affairs and gave news commentaries on radio stations KMPC and KMTR (now KLAC); became political editor, Fortnight magazine; wrote regular columns for the Los Angeles Daily News and Los Angeles Times; died in Toulouse, France, 1950.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of Flatau's radio broadcast scripts with related news clippings. Also includes clippings of his regular columns for the Los Angeles Daily News and Los Angeles Times.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Articles and newspaper columns (Boxes 3-4).
Radio broadcast scripts and ephemera (Boxes 1-2,3,5).
Research material on atomic bomb (Box 5).
Journalists -- United States -- Archives.; Radio journalists -- United States -- Archives.; Flatau, Kurt Louis, 1895-1950--Archives.
- Articles
  - Spain
    - Various titles, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- L'union Nouvelle Column
  - Clippings and Issues
    - 1940s. (Box 4)
- Los Angeles Daily News Column
  - Clippings and Issues
    - 1940s. (Box 4)
- Los Angeles Times Column
  - Clippings and Issues
    - 1940s. (Box 4)
  - Correspondence
    - Letter from [signature illegible], 1950 July 24. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Political Writings
  - France
    - Letter to American Ambassador from O.D. Keep, publisher of Fortnight. Copies of Fortnight, 1950 July 24. 1950. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Radio Broadcasts
  - General
    - Epehemera. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - KLAC
    - Scripts, 1946 March-June. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - KMPC
    - Scripts, 1942. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Scripts, 1943 February-May. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Scripts, 1943 June-September. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Scripts, 1943 October-December. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Scripts, 1944 January. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Scripts, 1944 February. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Scripts, 1944 March. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - KMTR
    - Scripts, 1944 May. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Scripts, 1944 June. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Scripts, 1944 July. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Scripts, 1944 August. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Scripts, 1944 September. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Scripts, 1944 October. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Scripts, 1944 November. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Scripts, 1944 December. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Scripts, 1945 January-February. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Scripts, 1945 March-April. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Scripts, 1945 May-June. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Scripts, 1945 July-August. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Scripts, 1945 September-October. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Scripts, 1945 November-December. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Scripts, 1946 January-March. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Research Material
  - Atomic Bomb
    - No further description available. (Box 5, Folder 5)